<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://engitom.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://engitom.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-29T09:52:09+00:00</updated><id>https://engitom.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Engi’s Exchanges</title><subtitle>Learning experiences</subtitle><author><name>Tom Zhang</name><email>txzhang@caltech.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Nothing Batter</title><link href="https://engitom.github.io/music/art/travel/gaming/youtube/food/baking/nothing-batter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nothing Batter" /><published>2025-11-29T07:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-29T07:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://engitom.github.io/music/art/travel/gaming/youtube/food/baking/nothing-batter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://engitom.github.io/music/art/travel/gaming/youtube/food/baking/nothing-batter/"><![CDATA[<p>“A post about talking about writing a post?” — W</p>

<h2 id="deja-vu">Deja Vu</h2>
<p>In HK I was shocked by Shek O Beach because I saw a scene straight out of an art book from a middle school art class. The rocks, beach, and coastline looked exactly the same as a drawing I did back then.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/assets/images/olddrawing.jpg" alt="alttext" />
2019 landscape color pencil drawing of coastline.</p>

<p>It was kind of magical until I realized that there’s probably hundreds of coastlines just like the one at Shek O with big red rocks and a mountain on the right side of the ocean.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/assets/images/shekobeach.jpg" alt="alttext" />
Shek O Beach coastline.</p>

<h3 id="dj-vu">DJ Vu</h3>
<p>My friend T was hosting DJ lessons for everyone who was interested in DJing for Ravery and I signed up for a quick lesson.</p>

<p>I didn’t expect that I would become good enough to DJ at Ravery, but setting up my own transitions and being able to explore nostalgic songs from the 2010s was actually a lot of fun.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/assets/images/raverydj.jpg" alt="alttext" />
Me DJing at Ravery.</p>

<p>However, one issue I have with Ravery is that there’s so much going on with food and games that there’s no one on the dance floor from 10 to 11.</p>

<p>Despite my complaints as a new DJ, this was actually the best Ravery I’ve been to.</p>

<h2 id="hollow-knight">Hollow Knight</h2>
<p>is a great game that is quite difficult for people who are not used to movement-based games, but once you figure out how to pogo<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, it becomes very fun.</p>

<p>The music and art are also amazing, and I really appreciate the cute/creepy insect aesthetic.</p>

<h2 id="silksong">Silksong</h2>
<p>felt a bit more clunky when getting started, but I eventually got used to the movement.</p>

<h3 id="old-habits">Old Habits</h3>
<p>I seem to explore more than I’m supposed to and end up going into late-game fights when I’m severely undergeared. For example, I went to fight some ants, which was one of the most terrifying things ever.</p>

<p>They all have their own complex attack/dodge patterns, even though they aren’t boss mobs, and also take 20 hits to defeat without any damage upgrades.</p>

<p>This also happened when I played the prev game because I would find bosses before I found any upgrades, like there was some kind of jumping spider that also spit lava which took me about 20 attempts, and I don’t think there was even a good reward after that.</p>

<h3 id="new-habits">New Habits</h3>
<p>I’ve been trying to do 100 push-ups and 100 squats every day and it’s gone decently well so far, since I feel much more healthy every day.</p>

<p>I even set up a website to let me keep track of it, where I have a counter for how many glasses of water I’ve drank so far, and whether I’ve played guitar/drawn/written.</p>

<h2 id="down-with-the-sickness">Down with the Sickness</h2>
<p>I may have mentioned this before, but since I don’t get sick that often, I get nostalgic about the last time I was sick, which was right after I got back from Japan last spring.</p>

<p>My hypothesis is that it has something to do with the loss of smell and the way that memories and smells are intertwined.</p>

<h3 id="orange-car">Orange Car</h3>
<p>I visited Prof. W’s house and they have 3 very nice cats. The orange cat seemed to really like me because it kept coming up to smell me. However, I was too engrossed in eating chocolate chip cookies to pick it up. Maybe next time.</p>

<h3 id="thankful">Thankful</h3>
<p>One thing that I’m really thankful for at Caltech is that the lights in the hallways are always on, so there’s probably not going to be any scary monsters chasing me to my room at night.</p>

<p>Also, the beds are all lofted, so there’s no room for monsters to crawl under and hide in.</p>

<h2 id="tubers">Tubers</h2>
<p>I was talking to W, M, and J at RD earlier and we were talking about my blog.</p>

<p>Sometimes I think about making YouTube videos again but perhaps more in a artistic way kind of like VSauce or Solar Sands with some overarching narrative but with interesting ideas throughout jumping between topics.</p>

<p>I think that if I went to any other school, that it would be possible to spend a ton of time on this and perhaps have a successful channel, but as of right now, it doesn’t seem like a possibility.</p>

<h3 id="if-i-did">If I did</h3>
<p>I would probably make a video with the theme of perspective, the central question being, “Are attractive people bad people?” as a bit of clickbait, and then incorporating humor, science, and art to make a broader point about the importance of perspective.</p>

<h4 id="frieren">Frieren</h4>
<p>There’s been a bit of a meme in the art community about how to draw portraits from the 45 degrees below and to the side angle, with a pretty funny drawing of Frieren from the anime of the same name.</p>

<p>This reveals how art strives to portray subjects but artists don’t focus enough on perspective. Too often do people draw from the exact same perspective, head-on or 45 degrees to the side. Some might say this angle has been perfected, but future artists may see it as backward and uncreative.</p>

<h4 id="artificial-intelligence">ARTificial Intelligence</h4>
<p>Then, I’d use ChatGPT and have it rate the attractiveness of 100 prisoner mugshots from 0 to 100, and compare the ratings to 100 images of random people.</p>

<p>Depending on the result, I’d make some sort of point about confounding variables but I can’t be certain until I actually do that.</p>

<h4 id="morality">Morality</h4>
<p>Then I’d ask, “Was what I just did moral?” Perhaps an excuse could be that I wasn’t the one who placed judgement on the prisoners on their looks nor actions. But is handing judgement off to an AI moral? Is it okay to judge the appearances of random people?</p>

<p>Then I’d reveal that the picture of “random people” are actually people that do not exist from <a href="https://thispersondoesnotexist.com">https://thispersondoesnotexist.com</a>.</p>

<h4 id="stories">Stories</h4>
<p>Many children’s stories revolve around concepts of the correlation between external and internal beauty, including:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The Ugly Duckling</li>
  <li>Beauty and the Beast</li>
  <li>The Frog Prince</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="blind-leading-the-blind">Blind Leading the Blind</h4>
<p>Perhaps a segment about being blind and how they avoid the concerns of appearance, interjected by a scientific sequence on how blind people can hear better than others, maybe something about echolocation.</p>

<h2 id="nothing-batter">Nothing Batter</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>“There’s nothing better than some flatbread and honey butter.” — Outdoor Boys.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve been binging YT vids from the channel <a href="https://www.youtube.com/outdoorboys">Outdoor Boys</a> a lot lately.</p>

<p>Here’s a video tutorial:</p>

<!-- Courtesy of embedresponsively.com //-->

<div class="responsive-video-container">
    <iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/hi4Df_gJgkw" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
  </div>

<h3 id="something-batter">Something Batter</h3>
<p>I was trying to make some dough before Thanksgiving dinner and a fire alarm got set off!</p>

<p>So, I was outside with my hand in the ziploc bag with the siren going off and everyone watching me was giving me these weird looks.</p>

<p>Turns out I didn’t put enough flour into the bag because the correct ratio of flour:water is 5:3 but I had some sort of concoction/solution where it was like 10% flour and 90% water.</p>

<p>However, after adding flour and mixing, I placed it in a bowl in the fridge and waited a few hours for it to expand (yeast produces gas).</p>

<h3 id="underrated">Underrated</h3>
<p>I cooked some on a pan around midnight with my roommate T and dipped it in honey butter and let me just say that it was DELICIOUS!</p>

<p>The day after, I made some for the other people who stayed over Thanksgiving and I think most of them really liked it.</p>

<p>I was trying to convince C to eat it and they asked, “What’s in it?”</p>

<p>“Dough!” was the answer.</p>

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Pogo: Downslash in mid-air at an enemy/obstacle to go upward <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Tom Zhang</name><email>txzhang@caltech.edu</email></author><category term="Music" /><category term="Art" /><category term="Travel" /><category term="Gaming" /><category term="YouTube" /><category term="Food" /><category term="Baking" /><category term="Hongkong" /><category term="Silksong" /><category term="Frieren" /><category term="Flatbread" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“A post about talking about writing a post?” — W]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buckets</title><link href="https://engitom.github.io/school/reflection/mindset/buckets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buckets" /><published>2025-10-10T07:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-10T07:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://engitom.github.io/school/reflection/mindset/buckets</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://engitom.github.io/school/reflection/mindset/buckets/"><![CDATA[<p>“Reality is stranger than fiction.” — Rohan Kishibe</p>

<h2 id="broken-blog">Broken Blog</h2>
<p>So, I think there was some kind of SSL error with my blog and I had to ask ChatGPT and Github Copilot a lot of questions because I have no idea what’s going on with these processes.</p>

<h2 id="fragrant-port">Fragrant Port</h2>
<p>I went to Hongkong over the Sep 4-7 weekend, rode some boats, saw some friends, and ate some egg tarts. I know it’s strange to include in this post instead of the previous one, but “Neon” is such a long post already.</p>

<h3 id="hku">HKU</h3>
<p>I went to a business course lecture with my friend C and the lecturer said there were 300 students and 5 subclasses with 60 students each. Standard referencing rubric rather than curve grading. 6 or 7 students per group in a project where they try to make a business plan proposal.</p>

<p>Prof drew a distinction between app/product and business, because the product does not guarantee profitability long term. He discussed how HK PCCW tried streaming movies at home long before Netflix and he was one of the first trial users but it was way too slow.</p>

<h3 id="reality">Reality</h3>
<p>HK is kind of like the Chinatown of China, because walking around you could kind of sense how similar Chinatown in Manhattan is to HK.</p>

<p>There are quite a few smokers in HK, and many are women, which I found quite interesting. However, a lot of the cigarettes in HK smell kind of like candy, which was quite strange, not sure what they put in there.</p>

<h3 id="seaside">Seaside</h3>
<p>I went to Tai O, a seaside village where the houses were on stilts. It felt like there weren’t many locals, but I did see like 10 kids playing around who seemed to be from the area.</p>

<p>Since it was low tide, I went out onto the rocks and my shoes got quite dirty from stepping into the soft mud when I thought it would be more solid.</p>

<p>I was wondering how kids here go to school, and I watched a movie on the plane called 《多幸运遇见你》 about how kids in a fishing village in China cannot get a good education because teachers don’t want to teach there. However, in Tai O, there seems to be sufficient schools and the kids just take the bus.</p>

<h3 id="must-have-been-the-wind">Must have been the wind</h3>
<p>There are quite a few reviews on Chinese forums harshly criticizing the movie, but it wasn’t as bad as they say because it was a chance to get perspective on how uneducated parents view education.</p>

<p>For one of the students, his dad doesn’t want him to go to school anymore because it makes more sense to teach the kid how to fish, where one net cast could be worth thousands of dollars. However, the family gets scammed out of tens of thousands of dollars and the dad decides to send the kid to school because he needs to know math to not repeat that.</p>

<h3 id="public-transportation">Public transportation</h3>
<p>The train and bus system in HK is pretty good, but I don’t like how there aren’t any downward escalators in even some of the biggest stations in HK. I don’t like it because I’m lazy, but it’s quite inconvenient for the elderly, who have to squeeze on the elevator with the baby strollers and regular lazy people.</p>

<p>Things should work out since there are less babies and more elderly these days.</p>

<h2 id="scientific-ethics">Scientific Ethics</h2>
<p>Ethics in science is quite complicated because most of the problems in ethics involve things which do not even exist yet. It is not the nature of the scientific procedure, but rather the act of the study itself.</p>

<p>For example, while I was watching an Instagram reel about how beekeepers squash new queen larvae to prevent a bee civil war, I wondered about the ethics of even conducting an experiment based on this phenomenon.</p>

<p>If anyone wished to study bee civil wars, they would be responsible for the deaths of thousands of bees because they would need to manufacture this in a controlled environment repeatedly, which seems pretty messed up.</p>

<h2 id="coursework">Coursework</h2>
<ul>
  <li>ACM 104: Applied Linear Algebra</li>
  <li>ACM 116: Probability Models</li>
  <li>BEM 109: Finance of China</li>
  <li>BEM 131: International Trade</li>
  <li>CS 164: Compilers</li>
</ul>

<p>I was thinking about taking Ph/CS 219: Quantum Computing this spring with John Preskill. According to M, there’s no need to take quantum mechanics before quantum computing, so I’ll just do it since I took too many of the spring term ML courses already.</p>

<p>Also, one of my friends T is interested in the content of 219 since she’s in quantum computing at a different school, so it would be interesting to see if there are any differences.</p>

<h2 id="dj-school">DJ School</h2>
<p>T, one of my good friends and amazing DJ, was giving a mini-class on how to DJ.</p>

<p>Essentially, DJs are trying to combine two songs in a nice way and transition between them until the event is over.</p>

<p>Me, A, V and some of the underclassmen were learning and at the end we tried to do our own transitions which went quite poorly, but then T showed us how it’s actually done, which was very impressive.</p>

<h3 id="round-and-round">Round and Round</h3>
<p>Before that, there was rotation, which was a lot of fun this year and I helped organize some of the events for Avery House.</p>

<p>At karaoke, I was running the table and was completely overwhelmed and had a terrible time. I believe the word is “crashout.”</p>

<p>Normally, T would be there to help run it, but I was operating the table basically by myself and had to do three things simultaneously:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Turn off the mics of the screamers, which requires quite a bit of testing</li>
  <li>Control the volume of the music and mics</li>
  <li>Take song requests and queue new songs</li>
</ol>

<p>This doesn’t sound too complicated, but trying to do it yourself for the first time is a very stressful process.</p>

<h3 id="reflection">Reflection</h3>
<p>When I was taking a shower that night, I thought about why I was feeling like shit, and realized that it was basically just in my head.</p>

<p>Instead of being angry at the people screaming into the mics, I should just relax and have fun instead. It’s all about attitude, just like fishing.</p>

<h3 id="laggy">Laggy</h3>
<p>When I came back to campus, my sleep was only about 7 hours per night, but I felt amazing waking up every single day.</p>

<p>In fact, I was extremely upbeat to a strange degree the morning after the shower. I was talking very fast and making a lot of jokes.</p>

<p>I’m not sure what happened, but by week 3 of class, that attitude was completely gone. I now need to sleep 9 hours like I did before and I always feel some kind of pressure.</p>

<p>In some ways, that felt like I was burning away my lifeforce in exchange for that kind of attitude. It felt inorganic, like the positivity was just swelling out of me.</p>

<h3 id="deserved">Deserved</h3>
<p>I don’t think it’s sustainable to feel that enlightened state forever. But I think it’s possible to move in that direction slowly over time.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tom Zhang</name><email>txzhang@caltech.edu</email></author><category term="School" /><category term="Reflection" /><category term="Mindset" /><category term="Courses" /><category term="Rotation" /><category term="DJ" /><category term="Jetlag" /><category term="Hongkong" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Reality is stranger than fiction.” — Rohan Kishibe]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Neon</title><link href="https://engitom.github.io/work/travel/hobbies/art/food/physics/neon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neon" /><published>2025-09-10T07:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-10T07:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://engitom.github.io/work/travel/hobbies/art/food/physics/neon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://engitom.github.io/work/travel/hobbies/art/food/physics/neon/"><![CDATA[<p>“We’ll never stop this train.” — John Mayer</p>

<div class="embed-spotify-song">
    <iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/7AtsEX4pJqmAaIajlMwaPU" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true" allow="encrypted-media">
    </iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="lessons-from-fishing">Lessons from Fishing</h2>
<ol>
  <li>Success is a mindset</li>
</ol>

<p>The way you feel depends a lot on what you perceive as success.</p>

<p>If you set the goal as being able to achieve some kind of probabilistic thing like catching a fish, you will either leave satisfied or dejected.
Don’t base your success off of a random event.</p>

<p>Instead, try to think about improvement and practice. If you make your goal to improve the accuracy and timings of your casts and retrieves, that will bring much more satisfaction because you will never be in that state of sadness after failing to reach your arbitrary goal.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Every system fails at the weakest link</li>
</ol>

<p>When I was learning to tie fishing knots (still am), I got snagged on the pier. It wasn’t the rod that broke, not the string, but the knot that untangles.</p>

<h2 id="flashing-lights-lights">Flashing… Lights? Lights?</h2>
<p>Bathroom at office had autoflush and in the beginning I kept getting splashed randomly because the lights would always turn blue and red and I had no idea what it meant. Eventually, I figured out the ordering:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Dark: Has not detected object</li>
  <li>Blue: Has detected object</li>
  <li>Red: Secure, if distance increases, go next stage</li>
  <li>Flashing red: Armed, if you are too far for too long, fshh…</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="liminal">Liminal</h2>
<p>While watching the Solar Sands video below, I knew that the picture was generated by a GAN (generative adversarial networks) or something but…</p>

<!-- Courtesy of embedresponsively.com //-->

<div class="responsive-video-container">
    <iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/0F7XBwFwA-M" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
  </div>

<p>He mentioned the series of albums starting with the below, which describes each stage of dementia.</p>

<div class="embed-spotify-song">
    <iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/0BE7TLLZoUhr9M8RlmFY3T" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true" allow="encrypted-media">
    </iframe>
</div>

<p>I didn’t listen to the whole thing because I was listening to it at work and it was making my mind completely fuzzy, which I guess is the intended effect, but I do recommend giving each stage a sample.</p>

<h3 id="its-just-a-burning-memory">It’s just a burning memory</h3>
<p>I wonder what it would be like to not be able to remember anything; it’s scary but more in an <em>inescapable</em> way like claustrophobia as opposed to creepy-looking things like spiders or something.</p>

<p>One of the scariest stands in <em>JoJo</em> only allows the affected to remember 3 things at once. If you learn a fourth thing, the first thing gets deleted from your mind.</p>

<h2 id="food-hawk">Food Hawk</h2>
<p>I was complaining to a Singaporean friend of a friend about the terrible food in Singapore and then they said to stop trying restaurants and to just eat at hawker stalls.</p>

<p>The idea slipped my mind because I thought I basically tried every kind of hawker stall until I realized that just going to the same two for lunch every day does not count as having seen every single hawker stall.</p>

<p>There truly is a wealth of food culture in Singapore. Even though some have become commercialized trash, many of the stalls have properly distilled Southeast Asia’s spirit and culture.</p>

<h3 id="friend-kway-teow">Friend Kway Teow</h3>
<p>When I sat down at a Chinatown Complex table at 2 PM with my fried kway teow, I noticed that the Indian dude diagonal to me was also eating from the same stall, so we got along quite well.</p>

<p>Tip: if you meet someone who wakes up at the same time as you just to go eat food, you are probably going to be friends.</p>

<p>I asked him where he thought the best food was and he recommended me to go to Outram Fried Kway Teow and Maxwell’s Tian Tian Chicken Rice.</p>

<p>However, I told him what I’m gonna tell you right now, which is that Tian Tian is incredibly overrated and you might as well just go to the chicken rice directly next to it because it’s a shorter line for basically the same thing.</p>

<h3 id="olivers-cheesecake">Oliver’s Cheesecake</h3>
<p>Then, he told me that there was a good cheesecake at place called quiec by Olivia, which was INCREIDBLE.</p>

<p>The cheese oozes out of the center and is deeply flavorful since it uses some blue cheese and is torched on top.</p>

<p>It’s like the Frank Pepe of cheesecake though, because the first few bites is delicious, and the final stretch is incredibly difficult.</p>

<h3 id="its-just-a-burning-memory-1">It’s just a burning memory</h3>
<p>After having not been at Caltech for so long, I’ve actually begun to miss Red Door. Perhaps I miss the food?</p>

<p>I’m not that senile (yet), but right now, I could really go for a corndog and, dare I say, a matcha latte.</p>

<h2 id="belief">Belief</h2>
<p>From going to places where people eat and how they eat, you can tell what they believe in.</p>

<p>People in Singapore love queuing for food, probably based on the assumption that the more people are queueing, the better the food is. However, that isn’t necessarily the case.</p>

<p>It could just be that the one with a line is preparing the food slower than the other stalls.</p>

<h2 id="crazy-train">Crazy Train</h2>
<p>After riding the subway so many times and listening to “Smooth Criminal” so many times (separately), I began to wonder how much you degrees could lean without falling over or slipping on the subway.</p>

<p>After thinking for some time, the two key variables to solve for are acceleration of the train and the friction coefficient between you and the floor.</p>

<ul>
  <li>If there’s not enough friction, you’ll slide sideways.</li>
  <li>If the train is not accelerating enough, you won’t be able to lean as much.</li>
</ul>

<p>For acceleration, I’m not too sure, but it takes $2$ minutes to go $1200$ meters. So, if you view the speed vs time graph, you get a kind of trapezoid where you increase to top speed, then flat, then drop down.</p>

<p>So, the area of this trapezoid is $1200$ meters, and let’s call the acceleration time $S$, in which case the area of this trapezoid can be represented as $(120-S)$ times the max speed.</p>

<p>The max speed is actually acceleration times $S$ under constant acceleration, so if you just plug in $10$ seconds for $S$, you get that the $a = 1.1 ms^{-2}$.</p>

<h3 id="stop-this-train">Stop This Train</h3>
<p>So, friction has to provide all of this acceleration for your body, but incorporating friction actually makes the problem way harder when using center of mass as reference point because then you have to solve position and angular equations.</p>

<p>Now, we do need to consider normal force if we want to know what happens with slipping, but I remember from high school physics that the coefficient of friction between wood and wood is $\mu = 0.3$, which means my feet are definitely not coming off the ground.</p>

<p>Let’s instead use the foot on the car as the point of reference, theta being angle with the ground. Say that your center of mass is $1$ meter above ground.</p>

<p>Then you have a torque from gravity $(g\cos(\theta))$ and opposite one from train acceleration, $(a \sin(\theta))$, on this point.</p>

<p>To solve for $\theta$, $g/a = \tan(\theta)$, so $\theta = \arctan(9)$ which is approximately $83 \degree$.</p>

<p>That’s quite a small lean, so it seems like we “are OK.”</p>

<h2 id="transformers">Transformers</h2>
<p>I’ve been self-studying transformers recently, which really built on my limited understanding from courses, but I’d like to attempt the Feynman technique of learning through teaching, so here is how a transformer works:</p>

<h3 id="data-format">Data Format</h3>
<p>I’ve noticed that understanding the type of data that goes into and comes out of the model really influences my understanding of how the interior mechanisms work, because I believe the inside is designed based on the outside, just like Alan Turing’s code breaker.</p>

<p>Transformers deal in sequence(s) of values, the values could be pixels, words, or locations. Whatever you want, as long as it’s a sequence. You give it some sequences and it learns how to predict future values based on all or some of the past values.</p>

<p>Example: I give the transformer a list of the paths I jog on, and the paths are sequences of locations at various times in the jog. Then, I give today’s starting point and it will guess the rest of the path.</p>

<h3 id="internal-workings">Internal Workings</h3>
<p>The transformer is made of attention blocks, which have a few variants, but the basic one is the attention layer which is a bunch of matrices, which goes to a 2-layer neural network, and this repeats a bunch of times.</p>

<p>Attention blocks take the input and project it into 3 matrices by separately multiplying by the query, key, and value matrices to get Q, K, and V. Once you get all three, you do Q times K times V to get the attention matrix.</p>

<p>But what do Q, K, and V mean?</p>
<ul>
  <li>Well say you have a word like “cat,” which has been turned into a vector. This vector becomes a vector in Q, K, and V, where Q asks what other words should matter to cat, K is the value of cat to other words, and V is the actual meaning of cat.</li>
</ul>

<p>What’s the point of the neural network?</p>
<ul>
  <li>Add nonlinearity to the model</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="neon-neon">Neon, Neon</h2>
<p>I’ve been a bit obsessed with John Mayer’s “Neon” so I’ve decided to buy a guitar in my last month in SG. My goal is to be able to play the live version at least without including the crazy solo part in the middle.</p>

<p>Note: By October, I am now OK at playing it. Feels like there is about 50% more to go.</p>

<h2 id="e">E</h2>
<p>I met up with my friend E, who used to be one of my profs, we caught up and talked a lot about research, AI, PhDs, the usual topics.</p>

<p>My current conflict over applying to PhD or going straight to a job is the state of funding in academia.</p>

<p>By the time I graduate in 2027, the funding situation will probably be the same. Perhaps this will lead to less applicants, but the job market is also bad, so more people may choose to delay their entry to the job market.</p>

<p>There also aren’t any clear stats on PhD applications per year, but Google Trends shows that the interest in “how to get into a phd program” has risen greatly, but “how to get a trade” has also risen, and has more interest.</p>

<p>I’m not sure what this means, perhaps a rejection of higher education or a rejection of office jobs.</p>

<h3 id="ew">EW</h3>
<p>I picked up my friends E and W from the airport and we had some kaya toast. It was kind of like seeing cartoon characters in real life.</p>

<p>E was watching JoJo on the plane and I totally forgot that they went to Singapore on the way to Egypt. After spending some time on Google Maps, I was able to find some of the locations that appeared:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Victoria Concert Hall: This is in a lot of the backgrounds</li>
  <li>Sultan Mosque: It’s not exactly the same building, but there’s a scene where it appears next to some train tracks.</li>
  <li>Shangri-la Singapore: Hotel that they stay at, seems close to the Takashimaya, which ChatGPT says is where lots of Japanese people stay in Singapore.</li>
  <li>Harborfront cable cars: I had no idea that the popular meme where Kakyoin goes “rerorerorero” happened in Singapore!</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="demon-slayer">Demon Slayer</h3>
<p>The new movie is pretty epic, but I realized that was just because I forgot the plot completely and that there’s just some emotional and animation value.</p>

<h2 id="master-cheng">Master Cheng</h2>
<p>One day on Instagram reels, I saw mention of an elderly twig artist by the name of Uncle Thien who hangs out on Owen Rd and makes portraits of people, which I found to be incredibly skillful.</p>

<p>So, I looked up Owen Rd, and it was two streets away from where I lived, Rangoon Rd. So, I decided to go on a walk one day after work to find him. I couldn’t find him along the road on the first day so I went home and tried again the next day.</p>

<p>I tried to reference the pictures of him online and noticed that there were two adjacent small yellow and black pillars which can only be found next to HDB carparks. So, I looked through every HDB carpark and found him next to a food center doing his thing.</p>

<h3 id="introductions">Introductions</h3>
<p>I introduced myself as a student from America and Shanghai who does art as a hobby and he asked for my “honored surname” which I said was Zhang, “as in octopus,” and he formed it with twigs on the floor and then I asked for his name and he said that his surname was Cheng, which was different from Thien from online.</p>

<p>I haven’t heard that surname before so he took the twigs from Zhang and formed the character Cheng on the pavement as well, which I understood.</p>

<p>I asked if I could do an interview for my school newspaper with him, and he politely refused, stating with a four-word proverb: “Fame brings disaster.” Which I found incredibly insightful; which is why I’m now writing it on my blog.</p>

<h3 id="basic-questions">Basic Questions</h3>
<p>Q: When did you start learning art?</p>

<p>A: I never really formally learned it, just self-studied.</p>

<p>Q: When did you start doing twig art?</p>

<p>A: Last year.</p>

<p>Q: How long did that drawing take?</p>

<p>A: Probably like an hour.</p>

<p>Q: When do you usually show up?</p>

<p>A: Probably like 5 or 6</p>

<p>Q: What are the eyes made of?</p>

<p>A: The right is a bit of cloth I cut up, the left is a rock I found.</p>

<p>Q: We’ve been squatting for a while (stands up), my legs are already (ma2) asleep, you must be very strong.</p>

<p>A: Yeah, if you don’t practice squatting it’s gonna be quite difficult to squat for this long.</p>

<p>Q: How do you usually start a portrait? Eyes? Hair?</p>

<p>A: You can start wherever you want, just make sure it’s a part that you are familiar with.</p>

<h3 id="so-long">So long</h3>
<p>He said he started doing twig art last year, but I found videos about him from 2020.</p>

<p>Three days after I met him, I again asked him when he started, and he said two years ago, so I think his memory may be somewhat fuzzy.</p>

<!-- Courtesy of embedresponsively.com //-->

<div class="responsive-video-container">
    <iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/6oBRUdo4T2w" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
  </div>

<p>I also learned a lot more from him in later lessons, but I suppose that can wait for a later day since this post is way too long.</p>

<p>One thing I will say is that it’s important to appreciate the people around you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tom Zhang</name><email>txzhang@caltech.edu</email></author><category term="Work" /><category term="Travel" /><category term="Hobbies" /><category term="Art" /><category term="Food" /><category term="Physics" /><category term="Fishing" /><category term="Singapore" /><category term="Bathroom" /><category term="Liminal" /><category term="Hawker" /><category term="Trains" /><category term="Cheng" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“We’ll never stop this train.” — John Mayer]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gone Fishin</title><link href="https://engitom.github.io/work/travel/gone-fishin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gone Fishin" /><published>2025-07-19T16:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-19T16:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://engitom.github.io/work/travel/gone-fishin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://engitom.github.io/work/travel/gone-fishin/"><![CDATA[<p>“Humans are…” — Player 456, <em>Squid Game</em></p>

<h2 id="spore">S’pore</h2>
<p>Straight off the plane, there’s just a gust of sauna air that hits you in the face, but the inside of Changi Airport has amazing architecture.</p>

<p>One of the things about Singapore is that the architecture incorporates a lot of greenery. I’ve always found it kind of artificial but it can be somewhat soothing.</p>

<h2 id="hard-work-cafe">Hard Work Cafe</h2>
<p>The company has quite a few snacks and drinks which makes work a lot more relaxing because whenever I’m losing focus I can just take a quick break.</p>

<h3 id="oil">Oil</h3>
<p>is quite different than stocks because the fundamentals are quite different because stocks are generally grounded by some concept of value through cash flows while oil has inherent value because people need oil to survive.</p>

<h3 id="hat-trader">Hat Trader</h3>
<p>In fact, it’s quite similar to the TF2 hat economy because people inherently desire hats and even though hats don’t provide cash flows, the prices persist anyway because of supply and demand.</p>

<h2 id="old-men-and-the-sea">Old Men and the Sea</h2>
<p>After viewing some fishing videos/tutorials, I bought some fishing gear for S$50 and went off to Bedok Jetty at East Coast Park to catch some fish in my tank top.</p>

<p>Had some lunch and then shamelessly asked a very nice boy the same age as me to help me set up my gear.</p>

<p>He was very willing to help and immediately I forgot to close the catch and started reeling up, which got the line all tangled up and he had to help me cut it and retie the line.</p>

<p>He caught quite a few sardines that day already and left after I caught my first fish, a little sardine, and gave it to him as a gift for helping me so much.</p>

<p>I fished until about 4 PM, then went to Labrador Jetty on the southwest side of the island and caught two more fish and went home after sunset.</p>

<h3 id="take-me-to-church">Take Me to Church</h3>
<p>I met one of my friend’s old friends from Singapore and since they invited me to church, I decided that I would go just to experience it because I’ve never been to a church outside of the U.S.</p>

<p>It started with a song by a drummer, a pianist, and a guitarist singer, and then the pastor talked about Deuteronomy and how it’s important to remember the past.</p>

<p>I remembered the amount of references to the Bible and especially Deuteronomy. in Ray Bradbury’s <em>Fahrenheit 451</em>, but didn’t actually know what Deuteronomy was about.</p>

<p>The choice makes a lot more sense in retrospect because F451 is also a book about remembering the past.</p>

<h3 id="diverse-city">Diverse City</h3>
<p>The church was mostly East Asian but there were some South Asians as well. I felt like it was sort of strange of the pastor to sometimes speak in Hokkien or Mandarin because the people that don’t understand will probably feel excluded by nature.</p>

<h2 id="extra-crispy">Extra Crispy</h2>
<p>After I got home from fishing, I took a shower and noticed that my skin got very tan in a funny pattern around my tank-top.</p>

<p>The next day, I noticed that I was getting some bubbles/blisters on the back of my arms where I couldn’t reach with sunscreen and I looked it up on ChatGPT because it’s much smarter than Google these days, and I got sunburned.</p>

<p>It seemed like I was only in the sun for a while because it was somewhat cloudy, but I guess the UV exposure was quite powerful since I was out there for 4 hours.</p>

<h3 id="ninjas">Ninjas?</h3>
<p>Singapore’s diversity is incredible despite its size. Everyone here says that it’s really big but it seems to only be about 50 km across the island.</p>

<p>I was walking back from buying aloe vera lotion from Watsons for my sunburn and saw two people in the underground tunnel dressed like ninjas, completely covered except for their eyes.</p>

<p>My first thought was, “Wow, I’ve never seen anyone dressed like that,” and my second thought was, “If I was wearing that while fishing, I wouldn’t have gotten this sunburn!”</p>

<p>I think they were Muslim women wearing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niqab">Niqabs</a>, which is quite rare because it seems that more people prefer to only cover the head.</p>

<h3 id="food-poisoning">Food Poisoning</h3>
<p>I’ve gotten food poisoning a few times, unfortunately, once from eating at an Indian hawker stall, and once from eating durian/shrimp that went bad.</p>

<p>I also felt quite bad after eating some strange-tasting oysters, but nothing actually happened.</p>

<p>Even though Singapore is so safe, it seems like the food is one thing it has yet to protect the people from.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tom Zhang</name><email>txzhang@caltech.edu</email></author><category term="Work" /><category term="Travel" /><category term="Fishing" /><category term="Singapore" /><category term="Church" /><category term="Food" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Humans are…” — Player 456, Squid Game]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Glass Half Full</title><link href="https://engitom.github.io/travel/advice/glass-half-full/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Glass Half Full" /><published>2025-06-14T16:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-14T16:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://engitom.github.io/travel/advice/glass-half-full</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://engitom.github.io/travel/advice/glass-half-full/"><![CDATA[<p>“Nothing lasts forever!” — A.H.</p>

<h2 id="popcorn">Popcorn</h2>
<p>I’ve always loved salty snacks like popcorn, pretzels, and chips.</p>

<p>Whenever I would watch a video while eating these snacks, I’d be done with the whole bag before I knew it.</p>

<p>Maybe I’m eating too fast, and I should try to slow down. But I’m mostly eating off of instinct. If I eat that fast then that’s what I’m meant to do.</p>

<h2 id="lays">Lays</h2>
<p>Time is like a bag of chips. Every minute, a chip gets eaten no matter what. Doesn’t matter what you do in ten minutes because after ten minutes you’ll have ten less minutes anyway.</p>

<p>How you enjoy those chips is your business. Perhaps some people will spend them studying or working or hanging out with friends. Personally, I try to waste as much of it as possible.</p>

<h3 id="cardboard">Cardboard</h3>
<p>Sometimes, when I think back to just things from a few months ago, they have a cardboard-like texture and everything is fuzzy. For me, writing is not really a way to recover the definition of the past, but to put more focus on the present.</p>

<p>So, I don’t really write as a historian. It’s more like I’ve packed every month into cardboard boxes to be put in the attic.</p>

<h3 id="tunneling">Tunneling</h3>
<p>I think the Caltech tunnels are one of the most interesting pieces of art I’ve ever seen. Not just because it’s mysterious, but because you can feel what others have felt in the exact same way. Hope, love, fear, faith.</p>

<p>Time is the currency of emotion. You don’t get to feel emotions unless you spend a little bit of time to obtain and experience them. If you spend too much time just on experiencing new things though, the emotions may become dulled and devalued.</p>

<h2 id="half-full">Half Full</h2>
<p>Sometimes I look forward to graduating but I’ve recently begun to miss the past. I guess that’s something that happens at the end of sophomore year.</p>

<p>On the bright side, there’s still two years left, and that’s great because I think only in the last year have I really begun to appreciate Caltech.</p>

<h3 id="nightmare">Nightmare</h3>
<p>J had a nightmare that he and I transferred to Columbia. Apparently I transferred to Columbia and then he was like, “I guess I’ll also transfer to Columbia.”</p>

<p>But we soon realized that Columbia is very sad compared to Caltech (even though neither of us have been to Columbia), and then we started crying LOL.</p>

<p>After he woke up, he was incredibly relieved because that would have really sucked.</p>

<p>Anyway, that nightmare just goes to show how the present should not be taken for granted.</p>

<h2 id="free-at-last">Free at Last</h2>
<p>It’s summer and I’m finally free from Caltech. I’ll be doing some oil trading at my internship in Singapore, which I’m really excited for. However, I’ve heard the weather is terrible, so I’m not really looking forward to that.</p>

<p>E and W are coming during the summer, which should be fun since I can show them around as a semi-local. I think I adapt relatively quickly, so I think I’ll be fine.</p>

<h2 id="advice-for-frosh">Advice for Frosh</h2>
<p>I’ve given advice quite a few times on this blog but it seems to change every time, so I hope I’m not contradicting myself.</p>

<p>What I’ve realized in the last few months is that being an extrovert is far superior to being an introvert in basically every situation.</p>

<h3 id="why-extrovert">Why extrovert?</h3>
<p>I think I remember thinking that lots of extroverts I knew were annoying, which I found is only true if the person is just loud and doesn’t say anything interesting.</p>

<p>However, just by nature of having more interactions with other people, extroverts get more opportunities to make connections which is much better than the alternative.</p>

<p>The main problem with being an introvert is that you can’t guarantee that anyone is going to talk to you, especially not later on.</p>

<h3 id="fear">Fear</h3>
<p>As an introvert myself, it’s sometimes hard to find the courage to just talk to people I don’t know, but that’s something that can be practiced.</p>

<p>It’s hard for people to change their personality. So, for the introverts reading this, I think that one solution is to go up to someone who is also an introvert and try to talk to them because you probably have similar personalities.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tom Zhang</name><email>txzhang@caltech.edu</email></author><category term="Travel" /><category term="Advice" /><category term="Time" /><category term="Singapore" /><category term="Japan" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Nothing lasts forever!” — A.H.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Art is Observation</title><link href="https://engitom.github.io/art/college/math/art-is-observation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Art is Observation" /><published>2025-05-03T07:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-03T07:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://engitom.github.io/art/college/math/art-is-observation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://engitom.github.io/art/college/math/art-is-observation/"><![CDATA[<p>“Just give up.” — Prof. Andrew Sinclair</p>

<h2 id="the-marriage-problem">The Marriage Problem</h2>
<p>In BEM 114, Hedge Funds, we learned about a version of <em>the marriage problem</em>:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Suppose you will meet 1,000 potential partners in your life,
    <ul>
      <li>Assume that your compatibility with partners follows an i.i.d. uniform distribution between [0, 1],</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>If you ask a partner to marry you, they will say yes,</li>
  <li>However, if you pass over a partner, you can never go back to ask them to marry you,</li>
</ul>

<p>Given this, what is the optimal strategy?</p>
<h3 id="backwards-induction">Backwards Induction</h3>
<p>begins by starting at the end and moving up to the beginning of the problem.</p>

<p>In this case, if there is only one person left to meet, then this person will have an expected compatibility of 0.5, since we are drawing from a uniform distribution from 0 to 1.</p>

<p>If the expected compatibility is 0.5, then anything over 0.5 is better than expected and under 0.5 is worse than expected. Essentially, we want to propose to anyone who is better than expected.</p>

<p>Well, we know what to do if there’s one person left, but what if there are more people remaining?</p>

<h3 id="hard-part">Hard Part</h3>
<p>If there is more than one person left, let’s define that as N+1 people left, and the minimum compatibility that we will accept to be A. Let’s also define the minimum compatibility we will accept at N people left to be B.</p>

<p>So, let’s try to find A from B using some case-by-case thinking with a hypothetical A’ which is a proxy for A:</p>
<ol>
  <li>If A’ is less than B, we would just want B</li>
  <li>If A’ is greater than B, we want whatever A’ is</li>
</ol>

<p>So, when A’ is in the range from 0 to B, we want B, and when A’ is in the range from B to 1, we want A’. Let’s try to find the average compatibility that we will accept across all A’ then, since that will be A.</p>

<p>To get the average compatibility for A’, we just average the <strong>score we are getting</strong> over the <strong>cases where that score will occur</strong>.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/assets/images/back_induct_graph.png" alt="backinductgraph" />
Case 1 is purple (left) and 2 is orange (right)<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, the areas together become A.</p>

<p>Specifically:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Purple is (B-0) * B, a square</li>
  <li>Orange is (1-B) * A’, but this is actually a trapezoidal shape (1-B) * (1+B) / 2, which is (1-B^2) / 2</li>
</ol>

<p>Adding these, we get A = 1/2 + B^2/2.</p>

<h3 id="methods">Methods</h3>
<p>Now, let’s write a quick Python script to calculate this A for many steps, just modify N and you can run this code by just copy-pasting the below into this <a href="https://www.programiz.com/python-programming/online-compiler/">online code runner</a>.</p>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">N</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1000</span> <span class="c1"># the number of people left
</span><span class="n">B</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">0.5</span> <span class="c1"># the initial B
</span><span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nb">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">N</span><span class="p">):</span> <span class="c1"># loop N times
</span>  <span class="n">A</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nb">pow</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">B</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="c1"># the formula described above
</span>  <span class="n">B</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">A</span> <span class="c1"># restart the process with B set as A
</span>
<span class="k">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">f</span><span class="s">"Minimum comptibility acceptable with </span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">N</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s"> people remaining: </span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">B</span><span class="si">:</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="mi">3</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>This gives the following output with different N:<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Minimum acceptible compatibilities at 1 people remaining: 0.500</p>

  <p>Minimum acceptible compatibilities at 10 people remaining: 0.861</p>

  <p>Minimum acceptible compatibilities at 50 people remaining: 0.964</p>

  <p>Minimum acceptible compatibilities at 100 people remaining: 0.981</p>

  <p>Minimum acceptible compatibilities at 500 people remaining: 0.996</p>

  <p>Minimum acceptible compatibilities at 1000 people remaining: 0.998</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="results">Results</h3>
<p>So, let’s graph this result from 1 to 1000:</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/assets/images/marriage_line_plot.png" alt="lineplotmarriageproblem" />
Line plot showing minimum acceptable compatibility at each remaining number of candidates in this variation of the Marriage Problem. I’ve also included a baseline for what some are willing to accept.</p>

<h3 id="discussion">Discussion</h3>
<p>So, as we can see, it rapidly goes from 0.5 to approaching 1, the model is saying, “If someone is not perfectly matched with you, then <em>just give up</em>.”</p>

<p>Now, this weird outcome may seem like a problem with the model: there may be external factors that we are not considering or some problem with the process.</p>

<p>These are valid concerns, since it’s unrealistic to not date anyone who isn’t an ideal match, but the gist of it is that you shouldn’t settle for less, and certainly not the <em>bare-minimum.</em><sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<h3 id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h3>
<p>Thanks to Professor Andrew Sinclair for including this variation of the Marriage Problem in “Lecture 8: Fixed Income and LTCM” of BEM 114: Hedge Funds as bonus slides on backwards induction.</p>

<p>If you are interested in exploring the code in a Python Notebook, check out this <a href="https://github.com/EngiTom/MarriageProblem">Github respository</a> or this <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1Tibjt5GbpHYTlDhTLTs5PpzROxkjTzex?usp=sharing">Google Colaboratory Notebook</a>.</p>

<p>If you don’t know how to run code, I suggest going to the Notebook and pressing Connect in the top right and then pressing the triangle “Play button” on all of the code blocks.</p>

<h2 id="art-is-observation">Art is Observation</h2>
<p>I got a bit distracted exploring that idea, but now we are back on track!</p>

<h3 id="jojos-reference">JoJo’s Reference</h3>
<p>In Part 4 of <em>JoJo’s Bizarre Adventure</em>, the manga artist Rohan Kishibe claims that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Reality is the energy that breathes life into a piece of work, and reality itself is entertainment.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Despite Rohan’s weird behavior, I agree completely with this statement because without understanding reality, or more specifically, <em>your reality</em>, you cannot portray that to other people to your fullest capability.</p>

<h3 id="learning-reality">Learning Reality</h3>
<p>Every time I learn how to draw something better, it feels really good. It’s like the feeling of reaching into a jar of candy and pulling out two pieces of candy.<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p>

<p>For example, when I learned in a reel that you can draw noses simply by drawing some horizontal lines, I was completely amazed and needed to try it out. It actually went extremely well and ‘m Ishocked by my abilities.</p>

<h3 id="back-to-the-drawing-board">Back to the drawing board</h3>
<p>I’ve been drawing my friends on the Avery UGT lounge whiteboard and those have ended up being really nice drawings that I’m quite proud of. Obviously there are big improvements to be made like the shapes of things and their dimensions, but overall, you can get the vibe of the person just by seeing the picture.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/assets/images/badapple.jpg" alt="badappledrawing" />
Snow White and her stand, “BAD APPLE”</p>

<p>My friend G drew Snow White on the board before I got to the lounge and so I turned SW into a JoJo’s character with a stand. I drew a dwarf with a funny hat with a cotton ball on top and called it “7 DWARVES” but then I named it “BAD APPLE” instead, after the song “Bad Apple” from Dance Dance Revolution.</p>

<div class="embed-spotify-song">
    <iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/57JRZbE80MLsYbmb24cPee" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true" allow="encrypted-media">
    </iframe>
</div>

<p>I think that this was the peak of my art, but it’s all based on my perception and observation of reality.</p>

<h3 id="back-to-work">Back to Work</h3>
<p>Well, the moment has passed. Gotta go do my midterms now.</p>

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>In case you are colorblind <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I know it’s off by one, but it doesn’t matter <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Which some are known to do <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Or maybe I’m just conditioned to love drawing like a dog. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Tom Zhang</name><email>txzhang@caltech.edu</email></author><category term="Art" /><category term="College" /><category term="Math" /><category term="Drawing" /><category term="Sketching" /><category term="Dating" /><category term="The Marriage Problem" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Just give up.” — Prof. Andrew Sinclair]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Works of Love</title><link href="https://engitom.github.io/travel/japan/life/sugar-is-not-sweet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Works of Love" /><published>2025-04-29T07:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-29T07:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://engitom.github.io/travel/japan/life/sugar-is-not-sweet</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://engitom.github.io/travel/japan/life/sugar-is-not-sweet/"><![CDATA[<p>“Time is Fine.” — E and Oji of 日榮軒</p>

<h2 id="candy">Candy</h2>
<p>Sugar is not necessarily the only thing that tastes sweet.</p>

<p>On this trip in Japan, I realized that happiness does not require much material. Perhaps to the extent that it affects health, but not more than that.</p>

<p>In Kyoto, next to the Kinkaku-Ji, the Golden Pavilion, there’s a <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/pLhMeFzzJJaGbsEv5">40-year-old sweets shop known as 日榮軒</a> run by a 94-year-old man and a 86-year-old woman (we call them Oji-chan and Oba-chan).</p>

<h3 id="the-happiest-place-on-earth">The Happiest Place on Earth</h3>
<p>is definitely not Disney World. In fact, Disney is not even up for debate. It’s an artificial amalgamation of neural manipulation, but this sweets shop is a place where you get to witness what true happiness is in the form of love.</p>

<p>It’s a work of love and love of work. I asked grandma what her favorite thing to make was, and she said that it was everything, “zenbu.” I knew she wasn’t just lying because there’s no way anything she didn’t like would have survived on that shelf of treasures through 40 years.</p>

<h3 id="laughter">Laughter</h3>
<p>We weren’t communicating very well, but we could get the gist of what we were saying to each other. With the help of Google Translate and Duolingo streaks, we were able to get some humor across:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Oba: What’s your schedule for the next few days?
E: Today, we are going back to Osaka. Tomorrow, we are coming back to see Kyoto. Tomorrow-morrow, we are going around Osaka. Tomorrow-morrow-morrow, we are flying back to Los Angeles. 
Everyone: LOL</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It was totally hilarious because E knew how to say tomorrow (ashita) but not the next day (asatte), so he just said “Ashita-ashita” and “Ashita-ashita-ashita!”</p>

<h3 id="embarrassment">Embarrassment</h3>
<p>At the end of the day, we took two pictures with them and were about to go back to Osaka, but Oji stopped us and tried to tell us to take the bus, drawing out a map in the process.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/assets/images/oji.jpg" alt="the real golden pavilion" />
K, A, R, R, E, T outside of 日榮軒 with Oji-chan</p>

<p>We tried to tell him that we can go back by ourselves and that we were going to take the subway.</p>

<p>I thought he kept yapping because he didn’t understand us saying we’re just gonna go to the subway because he doesn’t know how Google translate works, but when we left, it turned out that we were too far to walk to the subway and actually did need to take the bus.</p>

<p>However, we already walked the wrong way at that point and needed to walk to the next bus stop to avoid him seeing us walk back the wrong way LOL.</p>

<p>Before we left though, they gave us some free Daifukus, which are like mochis with filling. I’m not sure if this is some cosmicly unlikely event, but the mochis that she gave us were exactly the same colors as our clothes that day:</p>

<ul>
  <li>2 green</li>
  <li>2 white</li>
  <li>2 dark green</li>
</ul>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/assets/images/daifuku.jpg" alt="daifuku" />
6 Daifuku, made with love.</p>

<p>Note that the characters for daifuku are 大福, which means Big Happiness if you do a literal translation. What an accurate translation.</p>

<h3 id="tears-of-joy">Tears of Joy</h3>
<p>The next day, I had the idea of printing the pictures we took and framing them as a present for them. I actually lost the USB for a while in my suitcase (I have no idea why I put it there) and lost my cool for a bit.</p>

<p>We came back the next day to get more gifts for our classmates at Caltech<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> and to give them the pictures. In total, we probably spent like 200 bucks on sweets alone<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<h3 id="the-persistence-of-memory">The Persistence of Memory</h3>
<p>When we were talking to grandpa, he decided to once again start to tell us how to get to our next destination, which was the Fushimi Inari Shrine in southeast Kyoto.</p>

<p>This time, I took the advice and he drew a map which I took a picture of. Apparently, he’s memorized the bus and subway lines in Kyoto because he literally does not know how to use a phone since he was born during WW2.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/assets/images/map_of_love.jpg" alt="map_of_love" />
Map of Kyoto’s 204 bus route, drawn by Oji-chan</p>

<h3 id="bliss">Bliss</h3>
<p>By the end, even though we only spent a few moments together, everyone was crying and we hugged grandma and left to get in the bus-line. Before we got on the bus though, Oba-chan forced us to take some free sweets.</p>

<p>On the bus ride to the subway station, I ate the free sweets that she gave us, and even though you could tell there wasn’t much sugar in it, it’s still the sweetest thing I’ve ever tasted.</p>

<h2 id="onsen">Onsen</h2>
<p>The onsen/hot spring in Arimaonsen near Kobe is really nice. I recommend eating the amazing beef and then going for a soak in there.</p>

<h3 id="parasytic-theory">Parasytic Theory</h3>
<p>Mosquitoes may serve a symbiotic relationship with humans because one of my friends told me about how she got bitten on the neck and it looked like a MASSIVE hickey.</p>

<p>She was even asked by the chancellor of the house about this bite mark and it was super embarrassing.</p>

<p>I used to know someone from high school who would only be romantically interested in those who had a partner already, and would immediately lose interest after the target broke up with their partner.</p>

<p>Perhaps in the evolution of human society and mosquitoes, those who accidentally got these hickey-like marks were perceived to be of higher worth because they got marked by another person.</p>

<p>Anatomically, it’s interesting because the neck is a place where there is both the easiest access to blood and where a person cannot reach with their own mouths.</p>

<h3 id="usb-memory">USB Memory</h3>
<p>I tried buying a USB storage disk in Japan but the guy at the counter didn’t know what storage was, so he kept trying to give me a converter.</p>

<p>R found it and it was actually called USB memory, which is kind of interesting that the word is memory rather than storage. Perhaps it means something about the way I perceive information as something that’s stored rather than something that contains a <em>memory</em>.</p>

<h3 id="time-is-fine">Time is Fine</h3>
<p>At one point in our discussion with grandpa, he and E were talking at the same time in Japanese and both of their words mixed together and ended up exactly translating to “時間は大丈夫” (jikan wa daijoubu), which means “Time is fine” or “Time to be fine” depending on your interpretation.</p>

<h3 id="so-its-the-same-type-of-class">So it’s the same type of class…</h3>
<p>as Math 3. Turns out, every class is just statistics. You really can’t avoid it at all these days.</p>

<p>I think stats should be taught in every high school and required over geometry, since all you need to know is the perimeter and area of a triangle, rectangle, and circle. Everything else in geometry is basically useless.</p>

<h3 id="flies">Flies</h3>
<p>In CS 179, Al was talking about how convolutional neural networks get really lost. A model might think that a panda is actually a monkey just with a bit of noise on top of the image.</p>

<p>Similarly, flies who have simple vision systems are more likely to bite horses than zebras because zebra stripes tend to <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/zebra-stripes-confuse-biting-flies-causing-them-abort-their-landings">confuse the hell out of flies up close.</a></p>

<p>Just another day of learning in <strong>GPU Programming</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="t-shirt-design">T-Shirt Design</h2>
<p>I submitted a design to the annual Caltech store contest and I think I have a relatively good shot at winning.</p>

<p>But if I lose, I might just print the shirt for myself because it’s a great design.</p>

<h3 id="mike-the-t-shirt-collector">Mike the T-Shirt Collector</h3>
<p>I competed in Hacktech this weekend and I met a dude called Mike who seemed to be a recruiter for some kind of company.</p>

<p>He mentioned how he loves collecting t-shirts from hackathons that he’s been to and that I was apparently the “famous Caltech student” who they’ve heard about from my teammates E, E, and T.</p>

<p>Apparently he had not seen a Caltech student that was participating in Hacktech until he met me which is totally insane and makes sense because everyone is so busy doing sets.</p>

<h3 id="mike-the-ceo">Mike the CEO</h3>
<p>On Sunday, we lost in the first round of judging but I went to the award ceremony for fun anyway and we actually won the “Best Use of Streamlit” award which was hilarious because I was the only one in my group remaining LOL.</p>

<p>Mike congratulated me and we added each other on Linkedin. He was criticizing the Linkedin app’s QR Code UI design, which was totally valid because the QR code feature is in the search bar.</p>

<h3 id="glory">Glory</h3>
<p>After <em>winning Hacktech</em>, I decided to post about it on Linkedin and wanted to tag Mike. However, I found on his page that he was CEO and co-founder which was kind of interesting.</p>

<p>Turns out, he’s the CEO and co-founder of Major League Hacking! There I was thinking he was just a t-shirt lover.</p>

<h2 id="the-california-tech">The California Tech</h2>
<p>As you know, I enjoy writing, so I started writing for <em>The California Tech</em> which is Caltech’s student newspaper.<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> Here are links to articles that I wrote for this edition:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://tech.caltech.edu/2025/04/22/places-you-shouldnt-be/">Places You Shouldn’t Be</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://tech.caltech.edu/2025/04/22/courses-that-dont-suck/">Courses That Don’t Suck</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="after-math">After math</h3>
<p>After the articles came out in the paper, my friend J was texting me and mentioned this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Also lol you could’ve also calculated the radius of a chicken nugget cake</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This was completely insane to me that someone would read my paper and I guess it’s also still crazy that people still read this blog but thanks everyone.</p>

<h3 id="arc">ARC</h3>
<p>Apparently, my second article caused a stir in the Academic and Research Committee because my joking comments about CS 179: GPU Programming were seen as a potential course complaint.</p>

<p>However, R quickly shut it down by noting that “it’s just Tom,” which I was glad to hear because I would not want to cause any trouble for Al.</p>

<h2 id="ultimately">Ultimately</h2>
<p>Happiness is hard to find, but if it meets you, don’t let it slip away ever again.</p>

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>They loved the sweets, so you should go there too! <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>We were definitely the top customers of the week. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>This is also why I did not write on this blog for a while. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Tom Zhang</name><email>txzhang@caltech.edu</email></author><category term="Travel" /><category term="Japan" /><category term="Life" /><category term="Tokyo" /><category term="Kobe" /><category term="Osaka" /><category term="Kyoto" /><category term="Sweets" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Time is Fine.” — E and Oji of 日榮軒]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Shear Luck</title><link href="https://engitom.github.io/stoicism/college/teaching/gaming/shear-luck/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shear Luck" /><published>2025-03-10T07:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-10T07:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://engitom.github.io/stoicism/college/teaching/gaming/shear-luck</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://engitom.github.io/stoicism/college/teaching/gaming/shear-luck/"><![CDATA[<p>“Sheer Cold (Japanese: ぜったいれいど Absolute Zero) is an Ice-type one-hit knockout move introduced in Generation III.” — Bulbapedia</p>

<h2 id="stoicism">Stoicism</h2>
<p>It’s much easier to be a stoic with a good understanding of statistics because you realize just how indifferent randomness is to who you are.</p>

<p>Bad things happen to you not because there’s a higher power that has a personal vendetta against you, but simply because you happen to be on the other side of luck.</p>

<h3 id="epic-fails">Epic Fails</h3>
<p>It’s important to fail and be laughed at because you realize that the people laughing do not actually care about you personally. If it were any other combination of audience vs failer, the audience would always laugh.</p>

<p>I missed about 5 spikes in interhouse volleyball against some random house the other day and everyone was laughing, but it wasn’t anything personal, we won, and that was that.</p>

<p>It’s not like I haven’t been embarrassed before or anything; it was much worse when I was busking in Shanghai and nobody stopped to listen. That felt like the entire city was laughing at me, so who cares about 20 nerds?</p>

<h2 id="deliver">Deliver</h2>
<p>Teaching is also quite luck-based, since whether a student understands an idea is somewhat up to probability based on their background, mood, and various other factors.</p>

<p>I was at a middle school’s science night attempting to teach text compression through repeated phrases like “UMBO” in “WUMBOJUMBO” and there were two high schoolers who could not understand the lesson, but a five-year-old who got it immediately without much explanation.</p>

<h2 id="points-of-failure">Points of Failure</h2>
<p>I finished interviewing for a company last week and I’m not sure when the results will come out, but regardless of the outcome, I know that it can go either way.</p>

<p>So, even though I can’t completely avoid the stress, I am prepared for things to go either way. Taking a wider view, my future will be better than the present whether it’s a rejection or an offer.</p>

<h3 id="winners-curse">Winner’s Curse</h3>
<p>Some of my friends who play <em>Genshin Impact</em> decided to host a random pull party where we all try to pull for a really good character called Furina.</p>

<p>I have pretty incredible luck in the game, as I mentioned in a previous post, and I did end up getting Furina with only 50 pity<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, so I guess my streak of luck has continued, but that may not necessarily be a good thing.</p>

<p>By receiving a new character, I am incentivized to play the game more and lose more time on schoolwork and other projects. This could be seen as a negative rather than a positive.</p>

<h3 id="free-stuff">Free Stuff</h3>
<p>I’ve noticed that my roommate E really loves free stuff, and often does things just to get <em>free stuff</em> but I’ve realized that nothing is truly free because it costs time to acquire it.</p>

<p>He’s going to spend an entire week in Washington D.C. at the end of the quarter which is a pretty bad idea since it’s literally finals week, but everything is going to be paid for by some company.</p>

<h3 id="time">Time</h3>
<p>is the most valuable in my opinion, along with health, and only after that, is money even in consideration. But above money is probably personal relationships.</p>

<p>As I learned from Civ 6, no man is an island. Not only from the achievement, but also because I would spend hours on Civ rather than spending time with my friends, which turned out to be incredibly depressing.</p>

<h3 id="down-with-the-sickness">Down with the sickness</h3>
<p>I became sick the night before a quiz in finance and found out about the quiz the next day and asked to be excused from the quiz, but unfortunately the policy is that we must ask to be excused before the quiz but how are we supposed to know that we are sick beforehand?</p>

<p>I find this very strange because it incentivizes always buying the option to miss class, which is what students seem to be doing because only 15 students show up to class.</p>

<h2 id="who-is-">Who is ???</h2>
<p>The Ws recently moved into Avery House and me and J helped carry a grill up to their apartment. After that incredibly difficult lift, we were granted permission to enter the apartment and pet their cats.</p>

<p>I’ve never held a cat before, but they are very heavy and they are mostly fur in volume, I guess that’s how they get through tight gaps.</p>

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>The pity system automatically grants a 5-star character 50-50 after 75 pulls without receiving a 5-star character. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Tom Zhang</name><email>txzhang@caltech.edu</email></author><category term="Stoicism" /><category term="College" /><category term="Teaching" /><category term="Gaming" /><category term="Volleyball" /><category term="Teaching" /><category term="Interview" /><category term="Genshin" /><category term="CS42" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Sheer Cold (Japanese: ぜったいれいど Absolute Zero) is an Ice-type one-hit knockout move introduced in Generation III.” — Bulbapedia]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Atlantas</title><link href="https://engitom.github.io/travel/college/atlantas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atlantas" /><published>2025-02-24T08:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-24T08:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://engitom.github.io/travel/college/atlantas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://engitom.github.io/travel/college/atlantas/"><![CDATA[<p>“In the <em>very, very likely</em> eventt of a water landing…” — Spirit Flight Attendant</p>

<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2>
<p>Went to Georgia Tech (GT) with E, my roommate, to attend their new trading competition. Had fun, met up with friends, toured GT/Atlanta area.</p>

<h2 id="trading">Trading</h2>
<p>@ Georgia Tech seemed to be run decently well, at least an 8/10 on the trading competition scale, although there are still the usual problems.</p>

<p>Note: I have never been to a trading competition, but I kind of have an idea for how much worse it could have been.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<h3 id="smells-like-spirit-pt-1">Smells Like Spirit Pt. 1</h3>
<p>To get the full travel reimbursement, we rode Spirit Airlines for $246 roundtrip and I actually ran into C, a TA for CS42, at ATL airport, so we saved some Uber money on the way back.</p>

<p>Spirit did a lottery raffle on the way back where the person with a yellow sticker on their tray table wins a free flight. After watching Squid Game/going to a trading comp, this appears quite predatory because they are taking advantage of people’s inclination to gamble.</p>

<h3 id="model-student">Model Student</h3>
<p>I didn’t finish my homework for Ma 3 or CS 155 so I had to finish them between the competition rounds, and at the end during the competition.</p>

<p>I was actually running a matrix factorization script for CS 155 in Colab instead of playing with the competition Colab and drawing a Huffman Tree instead of doing some pathfinding problem.</p>

<h3 id="smells-like-spirit-pt-2">Smells Like Spirit Pt. 2</h3>
<p>After taking the red-eye to ATL, I certainly smelled really bad and I was wondering how much that affected the outcome of the physical token trading game.</p>

<p>Perhaps people were avoiding our team simply because we were stinky, or maybe we were creating a <em>trail of stink</em> that our opponents could not cross without suffering powerful nasal damage.</p>

<h2 id="old-new-friends">Old New Friends</h2>
<p>I met two friends at GT, P and K. P has appeared before in the 2024 July post<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.</p>

<h3 id="pnk">PnK</h3>
<p>Although our PnL<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> was not very good, at least we had PnK to show us around.</p>

<p>I met K a few years ago playing Minecraft Bedwars with P, and then transitioning to League during COVID. We’ve never met in person before but I guess we have now.</p>

<p>She might be coming to LA in May, so hopefully she visits Caltech and E and I can give her a tour.</p>

<h2 id="gtouring">GTouring</h2>
<p>GT’s campus is very large and it has many roads going through it which I felt was quite unsafe, and is evidenced by how P knows at least two people who get into car accidents every semester.</p>

<p>However, I think it is much nicer than Caltech’s campus because it is quite practical with roads cutting diagonally through most places, but also makes it harder to see new shortcuts.</p>

<h3 id="clough">Clough</h3>
<p>Clough Library is 7 stories tall and every study space contains the number of people you will see at Browne Dining Hall at Caltech. So, two of those and you would probably have more people than are at Caltech.</p>

<p>They have quite a lot of manga at the library and a lot of computers/monitors. However, the study spaces/pods require reservation because there are so many people.</p>

<p>I guess we need to do reservations too except most people seem to do homework in house lounges instead of the library.</p>

<h3 id="filming">Filming</h3>
<p>A portion of an <em>adult film</em> was filmed outside of the physics building at GT, or so I’ve heard.</p>

<p>In other news, the new Captain America movie (which E lost an online bet on) also did filming in Clough. At P’s lab building, Coda, they converted the outside of it to a Chinese ER two weeks ago for the new Karate Kid with Jackie Chan.</p>

<p>I don’t know why they’re still making Karate Kid after the Jaden Smith one but I guess they’re still going at it. P’s PI apparently got to meet Jackie Chan which is super cool. He should get back to making <em>Rush Hour 4</em> though.</p>

<h3 id="food-options">Food Options</h3>
<p>Food options at GT seems very plentiful compared to Caltech but after further analysis it’s actually just fast food that there are options for.</p>

<p>For good food, you generally need to drive off-campus or eat the same few restaurants.</p>

<p>However bad the restaurants around Caltech may be, at least we can drive off-campus for guaranteed S-tier food.</p>

<h3 id="fun-fact">Fun fact:</h3>
<p>I had a group hug with P and K at the end, so they also suffered massive nasal damage, probably. P tried to avoid it but he ran out of jukes a long time ago…</p>

<h2 id="uber">Uber</h2>
<p>We had two interesting Uber rides from and to ATL.</p>

<h3 id="fst-uber">fst Uber</h3>
<p>A young Kendrick fan picked us up from the airport except he wasn’t able to get into the correct pickup zone because he didn’t have the license to do pickups from the airport.</p>

<h3 id="snd-uber">snd Uber</h3>
<p>On the way back, the driver was calling a guy on the phone who seemed to have tricked him into losing $350 on some kind of gamble so he was basically just arguing with that guy the whole time.</p>

<h2 id="wayback">Wayback</h2>
<p>We actually ran into a TA for a Caltech class at ATL on the way back, so we hitched a ride and saved some Uber money.</p>

<h3 id="flight-or-lottery">Flight or lottery?</h3>
<p>Spirit did a lottery raffle on the way back where the person with a yellow sticker on their tray table wins a free flight. After watching Squid Game/going to a trading comp, this appears quite predatory because they are taking advantage of people’s inclination to gamble.</p>

<p>That may have sounded funny coming from someone who went to a literal gambling competition, but it seems very possible that people would be more inclined to come back just because there’s a raffle.</p>

<h3 id="rng">RNG</h3>
<p>B was sitting in the middle seat and there was a girl on the other side who was incredibly interesting.</p>

<p>She didn’t know how to put on the seatbelt at first and we had to tell her how to do it. She was trying to put it in backwards; perhaps she has never been on a plane before.</p>

<p>During the flight, she was sleeping and putting her leg up and pretty far into B’s territory, which made B quite uncomfortable, but it was manageable; much less annoying than the old dude in front snoring really loudly for 20 minutes.</p>

<p>Near the end though, the descending announcement woke everyone up but the girl was still half-asleep and she started grabbing B’s thighs very aggressively and B completely freaked out and did not know what to do.</p>

<p>I thought it was kind of hilarious that she was still half-asleep and doing that but I guess it wasn’t that funny to B.</p>

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>With worse cheating, information leaks, technical problems, problem design flaws. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>P is my middle school friend and he used to live in Japan. Now he is a sophomore at GT. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>PnL = Profit and Loss <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Tom Zhang</name><email>txzhang@caltech.edu</email></author><category term="Travel" /><category term="College" /><category term="Gatech" /><category term="Atlanta" /><category term="Georgia" /><category term="Trading" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“In the very, very likely eventt of a water landing…” — Spirit Flight Attendant]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Snow in Pasadena</title><link href="https://engitom.github.io/disasters/teaching/snow-in-pasadena/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Snow in Pasadena" /><published>2025-02-18T08:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-18T08:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://engitom.github.io/disasters/teaching/snow-in-pasadena</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://engitom.github.io/disasters/teaching/snow-in-pasadena/"><![CDATA[<p>“It’s your golden hour.” — JVKE</p>

<h2 id="city-of-gold">City of Gold</h2>
<p>People like to take photos during golden hour, which usually right before the sunset.</p>

<div class="embed-spotify-song">
    <iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/4yNk9iz9WVJikRFle3XEvn" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true" allow="encrypted-media">
    </iframe>
</div>

<p>The last few days in Pasadena, every hour of sunlight has been golden hour.</p>

<p>Sometimes, it even snows. Ashes, but still pretty.</p>

<h3 id="first-snow">First Snow</h3>
<p>Starting on Tuesday 7th, massive gusts of wind woke me up and there were torrents of leaves flying past my window.</p>

<p>Later, when I went to class, I thought it was a bit chilly and I talked to J about it. He said that we should definitely ask M, a friend who is quite the expert in meteorology.</p>

<p>M said it was just the Santa Ana winds.</p>

<h3 id="second-wind">Second Wind</h3>
<p>Apparently, there were 60 mph winds coming down the mountain from the north. Naturally, this knocked over a few power lines and caused some fires.</p>

<div class="embed-spotify-song">
    <iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/6yh3aP8HuImur7v8p1P8fz" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true" allow="encrypted-media">
    </iframe>
</div>

<p>At some time after dinner ~18:30, it smelled like grill night but it was unclear where the smell was from, but I could see some smoke in the north.</p>

<p>This was apparently the start of the Eaton Fire which spread east and west in Altadena around 8 miles and north and south 5 miles, covering 10.6k acres by the 8th, then 13.7k and 14k the following days.</p>

<p>I asked my brother whether the fires would reach the school and he replied that it was impossible because there just aren’t enough trees for the fire to jump to.</p>

<p>However, if the wind picks up again like it’s expected to, things may actually get really bad.</p>

<h3 id="crowd-control">Crowd Control</h3>
<p>At Caltech, most people have left to the south in Irvine or Orange County. Some people have even escaped to the Bay Area or the east coast.</p>

<p>The main reasons to escape include the uncertainty of water contamination and air pollution as a result of burning buildings with asbestos, benzene, lead, and all sorts of delicious chemicals.</p>

<div class="embed-spotify-song">
    <iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/77ISXDULTIOiUoKGyY1hFb" frameborder="0" allowtransparency="true" allow="encrypted-media">
    </iframe>
</div>

<p>In the midst of the chaos, there have been lootings and even more arson. While the cause of the big fires are unknown, it may be a mix of arson and the wind.</p>

<p>Incredibly, E ordered a lot of masks the day before the fire simply because he doesn’t like to wear sunscreen. Thanks to that, we had masks immediately when we needed it.</p>

<h2 id="fourth-wall">Fourth Wall</h2>
<p>Typically hiding behind a screen whenever there are bad things happening in the news, I’ve actually gone to the other side, a victim of nature’s plot.</p>

<p>If you look at an aerial photo of the Pacific Palisades, it appears to be as bad as various warzones. As a longtime player of <em>Enlisted</em>, the scenes reminded me of France from WW2 with buildings stripped to the bone.</p>

<h3 id="arcanist">Arcanist</h3>
<p>Some student took an amazing photo from the top floor of Caltech Hall and it looks exactly like Heimerdinger’s memory of the world collapsing from people using magic.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/assets/images/link" alt="alttext" />
View of Altadena from Caltech Hall</p>

<h2 id="how-to-survive-the-apocalypse">How to survive the apocalypse</h2>
<ol>
  <li>Get some bottled water</li>
  <li>Wear a mask</li>
  <li>Don’t go outside</li>
</ol>

<p>This is sounding an awfully lot like 2020 all over again, huh?</p>

<h2 id="cs42-notes-on-teaching">CS42 Notes on Teaching</h2>
<p>I’m taking a course CS42 on how to teach math and science and I have to do a weekly discussion question and take notes, so I guess I’ll just write it here:</p>

<h3 id="how-children-learn">How children learn:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Babies prefer clear images to blurry ones, kind of clever experiment where they rigged pacifier suction level to the focus of a TV</li>
  <li>Babies prefer learning new things due to habituation, when they get used to something they lose interest.</li>
  <li>Children have bad memories, so use chunking</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="computational-thinking">Computational thinking:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Everyone should learning how to think like a computer scientist</li>
  <li>Q: How can everyone learning to think like a computer scientist if there are not enough people who understand computational thinking in K-12 education to teach it? For instance, 170k students took AP CSP in 2024 but there are 17 million high school students in America, so 1% of all students are learning computational thinking.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="learning-objectives">Learning objectives:</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Objective before content</li>
  <li>Students should be able to ___</li>
  <li>Remember, understand, apply, analyze, evaluate, create</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="cooking-ingredients">Cooking ingredients</h2>
<p>Meat: Pork
Vegetable: Maybe asparagus or bean sprout stirfry</p>

<h3 id="what-really-happened">What really happened</h3>
<p>I bought some flank steak from trader joes along with some asparagus, bell pepper, and an onion.</p>

<p>For lunch, I made some rice (with way too much water) and stirfry beef + bell pepper + half an onion.</p>

<p>It wasn’t that great since I didn’t remember soy sauce for the stirfry and I also had to eat C’s leftover rice from a restaurant because my rice was so disgustingly mushy.</p>

<p>For dinner though, I made some adaptations with the use of soy sauce and putting less water in for the rice. I clearly didn’t put enough water because by the time the bottom was getting dry the rice was still hard.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-boys-do">What do boys do?</h2>
<p>I noticed that a lot of my classmates had a very boring childhood so I would like to explain some of the things that my friends and I did for fun.</p>

<h3 id="sounds">Sounds</h3>
<p>Whoever could make the strangest sound was highly respected, for example, I remember this kid Z was really good at making dolphin sounds, and another kid C who could burp the alphabet. Really impressive stuff.</p>

<p>There were also a variety of fart simulations like the armpit technique, along with the lesser-known kneepit variation.</p>

<h3 id="actions">Actions</h3>
<p>There’s a funny thing you can do with a hoodie which is putting one arm at your stomach and the other holding the empty sleeve, then moving them up and down in alternating fashion to create one of the most striking, almost inhuman, movements.</p>

<p>I did this to J yesterday and he said “I haven’t seen that since elementary school!”</p>

<p>Tag is one of the great games of all time with the freeze and zombie variations.</p>

<h2 id="more-notes-on-teaching">More notes on Teaching</h2>
<p>The annoying thing about teaching kids is that they can’t pay attention for more than a few seconds to something you say. This is really bad if you are trying to teach them a complex idea.</p>

<h3 id="what-kinds-of-practice-and-feedback-enhance-learning">What kinds of practice and feedback enhance learning</h3>
<p>Practice should be focused on the goal, like playing a whole piano piece vs focusing on just the hard part. Goal-directed practice + targeted feedback. Feedback must be linked to another opportunity to apply the skill.</p>

<h3 id="explanatory-power-of-the-hierarchy-of-student-needs">Explanatory Power of the Hierarchy of Student Needs</h3>
<p>Students need to feel safe emotionally and intellectually. They also need belonging/esteem which only few teachers can achieve. Some kind of inside joke seems like a good bonus, and I think DMO does a lot of things that help with student needs.</p>

<p>Inclusivity and equity are also mentioned as parallel to the goals of satisfying student needs. However, I wonder whether it would be <em>correct</em> to personally request a high-performance student to ask dumb questions to encourage insecure students to ask questions.</p>

<p>On an individual basis, this student is no longer equals with their peers, but other students have been led to believe that this student is also capable of asking bad questions.</p>

<h3 id="why-do-student-development-and-course-climate-matter-for-student-learning">Why Do Student Development and Course Climate Matter for Student Learning?</h3>
<p>Student’s level of development/maturity interacts with classroom climate.</p>

<p>The Chickering model suggests many dimensions like competence, emotions, autonomy, identity, purpose, integrity.</p>

<p>“Climate works in both blatant and subtle ways, and many well-intentioned or seemingly inconsequential decisions can have unintended negative effects with regard to climate.”</p>

<p>This tip would suggest that teachers cannot ensure every student’s needs are met, but they can improve the learning experience by adapting to students’ level of development.</p>

<p>In one of the examples, the professor does not call on women students in lecture because he doesn’t want to put them on the spot, which results in patronization. However, in a K-12 setting, it’s important to not put too much pressure on insecure students by singling them out because they may become even less confident in the future.</p>

<p>Q: If students are supposed to be treated equally, how can teachers shrink the gap between the <em>best</em> and <em>worst</em> students without treating them differently?</p>

<h3 id="responses">Responses</h3>
<p>I posted this question on the course forum and a student responded that “best” and “worst” are bad labeling and I agree because I don’t really agree with this framing in the first place, that’s why I put asterisks around them.</p>

<p>However, this student immediately said afterward that an example of how to resolve the problem is the way Caltech gives some first years supplemental math and writing courses</p>

<h2 id="ai">AI</h2>
<p>I was quite surprised to learn that data augmentation/hallucination is equivalent to regularization. I guess it makes sense because you are making the</p>

<h2 id="resnick-sustainability-institute">Resnick Sustainability Institute</h2>
<p>I recently attended a talk by a JPL Chief Scientist of some science directorate and it was super boring and I will probably not go to one of those talks again.</p>

<p>Essentially, the guy was talking about how he was asking people at JPL to write 3 pages each for his 90 page report on how climate change is going to influence the lab itself and LA county.</p>

<p>It seems completely pointless to write this kind of report because it’s just going to become a stack of paper on some officials’ desk which will inevitably get thrown in the trash after it’s never opened.</p>

<p>Even worse, this guy was more excited about the prospect of “holding a printed copy” of the report than helping anyone affected by the fires. By the way, he has a $400K budget for this report and 1000 copies are going to be printed and not publicized.</p>

<p>There’s a lot of</p>

<h3 id="cognitive-dissonance">Cognitive Dissonance</h3>
<p>where he wants to appear to make an impact (he mentions things like how the 2028 Olympics are going to be hosted in LA) but it’s also a report that people will never see or care about because it’s not going to be available to the public.</p>

<p>When one of the audience members (I think it was some hotshot at RSI because he’s at all of these talks) asked a question relating to wildfires, the first thing he responded with was how “successful” the webinar from a few weeks ago was, since it had 2000 people.</p>

<p>Then, he mentioned that after the fires happened, he was in talks with a coauthor who said that it may be better to change the whole report to just be about wildfires, but he quickly dismissed that idea because of all the time that already went into writing the paper (two months as of then).</p>

<p>So, basically he’s basically applying the sunk-cost fallacy because he would rather keep going on a doomed path where thousands of dollars have already been wasted than find better alternatives. Or maybe it’s actually impossible to have 30 people write 3 pages each in 2 months.</p>

<h2 id="anemoculus-collector">Anemoculus Collector</h2>
<p>Genshin is a game that I have disliked for many years, but I finally tried it and it’s actually quite fun. Essentially, you do quests, explore the world, fight monsters, do puzzles, and lootbox pull new characters.</p>

<p>I got lucky and pulled two five-star characters within 20 pulls, so that got me playing a bit too much every day.</p>

<h3 id="satisfying-parts">Satisfying Parts</h3>
<p>The fighting is quite satisfying initially because there are many elemental combinations that do bonus damage, so you can use one character of water type and attack with fire type later to <em>vaporize</em> the enemy. This teaches kids phase transitions pretty well, I guess.</p>

<p>Some parts of the story are incredibly interesting and the environment is very engaging, especially in the region based on Atlantis. The art quality is super good and it really immerses the player.</p>

<h3 id="unsatisfying-parts">Unsatisfying Parts</h3>
<p>If you pull a newer character, then you need to go far from the original continent to level them up which messes up the feeling of the intended progression, and sometimes it feels like you’re going places just so you can teleport to them later.</p>

<p>The stamina system is incredibly annoying because you can only run for a few seconds before you have to recharge and walk. If you run out of stamina while climbing a mountain or swimming, you fall/drown.</p>

<p>Some of the puzzles are super confusing because there is no explicit goal, it’s kind of like those physical puzzles where you are trying to open the box but there’s no rules given. I guess your enjoyment depends on how much you like that but for me it’s not that satisfying.</p>

<p>Mining ore is also annoying because you need a claymore (big sword) character to mine anything but you may have a better character so there’s no point in having that character in your party.</p>

<h2 id="genetic-algos-for-ensemble-blending-to-dmo">Genetic Algos for Ensemble Blending: to DMO</h2>
<p>I’m taking a machine learning course where we form teams and compete against each other to make the best model for some task like song popularity classification and my team had a pretty wild performance from last place 50th to 3rd to 26th.</p>

<p>My friend accidentally selected a terrible model from day 1 and that was averaged with the really good model made with genetic algorithms. We would have been 14th if there was no accident.</p>

<p>There’s a concept of blending model predictions together with a weighted average which can decrease variance in the predictions and hopefully predict better on the testing data.</p>

<p>So, I wrote a GA to crossbreed different sets of weights for 5 different models and the results were better than all the other stuff we tried.</p>

<h3 id="rbf-applied-ml">RBF: Applied ML</h3>
<p>The RBF kernel is the radial basis function kernel which can be applied to support vector machines for classification machine learning problems.</p>

<p>It also stands for something else which some of my friends used to describe my typical disposition.</p>

<h3 id="re-genetic-algos-for-ensemble-blending">Re: Genetic Algos for Ensemble Blending</h3>
<p>DMO wrote back a few days later that they couldn’t find a new CS teacher and that there’s only one semester of Applied Algorithms now, which is very unfortunate, but there are always ups and downs I guess.</p>]]></content><author><name>Tom Zhang</name><email>txzhang@caltech.edu</email></author><category term="Disasters" /><category term="Teaching" /><category term="Wildfires" /><category term="Genshin" /><category term="CS42" /><category term="Genetic Algorithms" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“It’s your golden hour.” — JVKE]]></summary></entry></feed>